Guide to the John David Hayes Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
John David Hayes Papers
1921-1969
RG 127
Yale University Divinity School Library
0.5
(1 box)
The papers include writings, biographical documentation, photographs, and a tape recording documenting Hayes' work in China. Hayes was a Presbyterian missionary in China from 1917 to 1952, serving primarily in the Peking area. He was involved in student, educational, and administrative work. Hayes was interned by the Japanese during World War II and imprisoned by the Communists in China from 1951 to 1952.
Hayes, John David, 1888-1957
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Hayes Family
Biographical / Historical
1888 Feb 23 Born in Tengchowfu, Shantung Province, China - son of Presbyterian missionaries Watson MacMillan Hayes and Margaret Young Hayes
1910 A.B., Princeton University
1911 Appointed Rhodes Scholar from Ohio as candidate from Wooster College (x'09)
1914 B.A., Oxford University, England
1914-1915 Service with Y.M.C.A. in France
1916 Married Barbara M. Kelman
1917 B.D., Princeton Theological Seminary
1917-1952 Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. missionary in China. Hayes was in charge of Presbyterian student Christian work in Peking, China, 1917-1943. He was also Executive Chairman of the American Presbyterian Mission, member of the China Council, member of the Board of Directors of Yenching University, and on various other boards for many years.
1918 -1931 Involved in various flood and famine relief projects
1925 -1942 Served on faculty and administration of College of Chinese Studies, Peking
1943 Mar - 1945 Sep Interned by Japanese authorities in Weihsien Civilian Assembly Centre, Shantung Province.
1948 Returned to China, serving in Kueiyang, Kweichow Province.
1949 -1951 Mar Taught at government university following Communist takeover
1951 Oct - 1952 Sep Jailed by Communists
1955 Went to Indonesia to work with students
1957 Died from injuries suffered in an automobile accident in Indonesia
Scope and Contents
Hayes' work with students in China, his administrative work, and his work in famine and flood relief are described in biographical accounts. Of particular interest are Hayes' writings regarding his period of Japanese internment and the "confessions" that Hayes was forced to write while imprisoned by the Communists.
Arrangement
I. Biographical documentation
II. Writings
III. Collected material
IV. Audio-visual material
Communism -- China; Hayes, John David, 1888-1957; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A -- Missions -- China
- Biographical Documentation, Series I
  - Chronology of Hayes family; c.v. of JDH; letter describing tasks in Indonesia (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Narrative account of JDH's life by his wife, Barbara Kelman Hayes (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Drafts and source material for BKH account (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Interview with JDH, "I Saw Red China from the Inside" ( U.S. News and World Report ); writings about JDH by Sam Dean; tributes to JDH following his death, 1953 - 1955, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Writings, Series II
  Scope and Contents
  The writings of JDH are arranged chronologically
  - "Report of the Shensi Investigation, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "The Kansu Report", 1921 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Untitled typescript document describing period of Weihsien internment, 1943 -1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "The Relationship between American Mission Work and the American Government" ("Confessions" of JDH written while imprisoned by Communists; handwritten and typescript copies, ca. 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memorandum of address given by Dr. John D. Hayes to the Rhodes Scholar luncheon Thursday, September 10, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "In and Out the Bamboo Curtain" - Wooster Alumni Bulletin; "Experiences in Red China"; transcription of "tape made informally in the home of friends in Washington, D. C.", 1954 -1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "The Invincible" (a play), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Collected Material, Series III
  - National Geographic article re. earthquake in Kansu Province (with illustrations from photographs by the Hayes-Hall Kansu Earthquake Relief Expedition, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Articles re. Communism in Asia, 1952-1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence of Barbara Kelman Hayes, 1944 - 1969,n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Audio-visual Material, Series IV
  - Photographs of Kansu Earthquake (33, with some duplicates), 1921 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Tape recording of radio program: "Facing Communism" (Box 1, Folder 15)